Maud Hayes Stick Papers PC.5073
State Archives of North Carolina
Maud Hayes Stick Papers
1905-1974
PC.5073
1.00
The Maud Hayes Stick Papers consist primarily of correspondence, but also include postcards, newspaper clippings, and ephemera. Much of the correspondence comes from Maud's family, including her husband, artist Frank Stick, as well as her mother Charlotte, her sister Helen, several of her brothers, and various nephews and nieces. There is a large amount of correspondence from David Stick, including early letters from his 1938 cross country hitch hiking trip, as well as extensive correspondence from him during his military service in the Marine Corps during World War II. This collection also includes correspondence, both to and from Maud, during her 1954 trip through Europe with two of her friends, Mally and Bucket. A diary Maud kept during this trip, and her passport and related documents, are also included in this collection, along with information on Hayes family genealogy.
Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972
Outer Banks History Center
Box Box 1
Box Box 2
Box Box 3
Box Box 4
Box Image Box 1
Box Image Box 2
Box Image Box 3
Gift
Arrangement
This collection is divided into three series: Correspondence, Personal Papers, and Photographs.
Access Restrictions
Available for research.
Biographical/Historical
Maud Hayes Stick (1889-1972) was born in Locust Grove, Md. to Owen and Charlotte "Lottie" Willis Hayes and raised on the eastern shore of Maryland and Delaware. Maud was the youngest of 10 children and one of only 3 girls (with Bertha and Helen). At the age of 18, she began working as an artist's model at Howard Pyle's art institute in Wilmington, Delaware. Maud's classic beauty made her one of Pyle's most sought after models. It was here that she met illustrator and writer Frank Stick in 1906 at a party hosted by one of Pyle's students. They were married in 1908.
While at the Pyle school, Maud continued to model for Frank and other Pyle school students. One of them, W. H. D. "Bill" Koerner, along with his wife Lillian, became close, lifelong friends of the Sticks. Maud was the model for one of Koerner's most famous paintings, "The Madonna of the Prairie," completed in 1921 and used as an illustration for Emerson Hough's story "The Covered Wagon" serialized in the Saturday Evening Post. Maud depicted the story's heroine, Molly Wingate, and even the author credited its success on the evocative presence immortalized in that painting.
Maud shared her husband's love of the outdoors and they enjoyed hunting, fishing, and camping together in the wilderness. They spent 1912-1914 living in a remote cottage at Squirrel Lake in northern Wisconsin, and then lived in the Chicago area, Wilmington, Del., and Interlaken, N.J., until discovering the Outer Banks in the mid-1920s.
In 1909, Maud gave birth to their first child, Charlotte. In 1919, the Sticks' second child David was born. That birthing aggravated a pre-existing hereditary disorder and left her so deaf that she would depend upon a hearing aid for the rest of her life.
In 1924, the Stick family of four joined forces with their close friends Bill and Lillian Koerner, who by then also had 2 children, to make an epic journey to the American West. Traveling in two old touring cars (the Sticks in a Dodge, the Koerners in a Buick), they braved dirt roads and extreme isolation to journey 5,000 miles in 4 months, ranging as far as Glacier National Park in northern Montana, camping and largely living off the land the whole way. Beginning in 1929, the Sticks would make the Outer Banks their primary home for the remainder of their lives. Frank and Maud dabbled in various business and community endeavors, while Frank played a pivotal role in the establishment of the Cape Hatteras National Seashore.
In 1954, Maud traveled throughout Europe with several women friends. Maud and Frank often wintered in Florida and took frequent trips to the Virgin Islands, where Frank was instrumental in the establishment of the Virgin Islands National Park. Maud died in Kitty Hawk, N.C. in 1972 after a long illness.
Stick, David
Custodial History
Formerly classified as 33MSS-73
Provenance
Donated by David Stick.
David Stick Papers from Stick, David, 1919-2009,(collection 3012)
Scope and Content
Ada Maud Hayes Stick (1889-1972) was born in Locust Grove, Maryland to Owen and Charlotte "Lottie" Willis Hayes. Maud, as she preferred to be called, was the youngest of ten children. By the age of 18, she was working as an artist's model at Howard Pyle's art institute in Wilmington, Delaware. Pyle was a well respected artist and illustrator. It was here that she met illustrator and writer Frank Stick, at a party hosted by Pyle's students. Maud and Frank Stick were married in 1908. The couple had two children, Charlotte in 1909 and David, (who would become a noted author, historian, and community organizer and philanthrapist) in 1919. Maud and Frank's mutual love of hunting and fishing led them to settle on the Outer Banks in 1929. Though Maud and Frank would make the Outer Banks their primary home for the remainder of their lives, the couple took frequent trips to the Virgin Islands and often wintered in Florida.
This collection consists primarily of correspondence, but also includes postcards and newspaper clippings.
Stick, David, 1919-2009; Stick, Frank; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972
- Finding Aid, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 1:1.1)
- Correspondence, 1917-1974; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972
  - General, 1925-1949; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 1:2.1)
  - General, 1950-1965; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 1:2.2)
  - General, 1966-1972; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 1:2.3)
  - General, undated; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 1:2.4)
  - Bill and Harriett Coppage, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 1:2.5)
  - Charlotte "Lottie" Hayes (Maud's Mother), PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 1:2.6)
  - Maud to Charlotte Hayes, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 1:2.7)
  - Clarence Hayes (Maud's Brother), PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 1:2.8)
  - Horton Hayes and Family (Maud's Brother), PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 1:2.9)
  - William Hayes and Family (Maud's Brother), PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 1:2.10)
  - Herbert Hoover's letter to Frank Stick regarding Stick's "Plow-Boy" with the army in the background, 1917; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 2:2.11)
  - Brock and Monty McMullen, 1968-1970; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 2:2.12)
  - Brock and Monty McMullen, 1971-1972; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 2:2.13)
  - Daniel Stick (Frank's Nephew), PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 2:2.14)
  - David Stick, 1935-1938; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 2:2.15)
  - David Stick, 1940-1941; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 2:2.16)
  - David Stick, 1942-1943; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 2:2.17)
  - David Stick, 1944-1945; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 2:2.18)
  - David and Phyllis Stick, 1948-1972; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 2:2.19)
  - Frank Stick, 1917-1934; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 3:2.20)
  - Frank Stick, 1935-1965; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 3:2.21)
  - Maud's letters to Frank Stick, 1931-1944; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 3:2.22)
  - Lydia Stick (Frank's mother), PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 3:2.23)
  - Helen Hayes Thather (Maud's sister), PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 3:2.24)
  - Richard Thatcher and Family (Maud's nephew), PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 3:2.25)
  - Bertha Hayes Vaughan (Maud's sister), PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 3:2.26)
  - Other Nieces and Nephews, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 3:2.27)
  - Condolence Letters Regarding Owen Hayes' Death (Maud's Father), PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 3:2.28)
  - Maud's Letters Written During her European Vacation, 1954; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 3:2.29)
  - Maud's Letters Received During her European Vacation, 1954; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 3:2.30)
  - Grandchildren and Great-grandchildren, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 3:2.31)
  - Article about Maud Stick in "The Showboat" by Fay Nelson and Related Correspondence, 1974; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 3:2.32)
  - Greeting Cards, notes and short letters; 2 from W. H. D. Koerner etchings; 1 with photo of Stick sons, 1971; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 3:2.33)
  - Post Cards; various sources, including one of "Skyco Lodge, Manteo, N.C." where the Stick family first lived at the Outer Banks in the 1930s, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:2.34)
- Personal Papers (Memorabilia from Maud Stick's Life), 1920s-1972; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972
  - Hayes Family Genealogy, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:3.1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Various Topics and Dates, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:3.2)
  - Ephemera from Maud Stick's Life, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:3.3)
  - War Ration Books, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:3.4)
  - Maud Stick's European Diary; one map of Europe with her itinerary traced, 1954; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:3.5)
  - Maud Stick's Passport and Supporting Documents, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:3.6)
  - Memorabilia from David Stick's childhood, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:3.7)
  - Warranty Deed: Dade County Florida, 1956; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:3.8)
  - Outer Banks Recreation Association & Duck Woods Golf Club, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:3.9)
  - Southern Shores, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:3.10)
  - Information about Frank Stick's Paintings, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:3.11)
  - Invoices (Medical Expenses), PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:3.12)
  - Summary of Stick Estate, PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:3.13)
  - "In Memory" monetary contributions at Maud Stick's death with condolence letters, 1972; PC.5073; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972 (Folder 4:3.14)
- Photographs, 44739; Stick, Maud Hayes, 1889-1972